We'll call it order, the regar is going to meet in my city council for Tuesday June 20th.
23 of a given puts on schedule personal chances and three claims
So Mayor members are Councils On Your Claim's List tonight
On page 2-5
Thereís an item listed RLI surety which has annual renewal
Of bond with mayor
Each review have an Annual Bond payment that comes due
This one happens to be for the mayor and so,
To avoid any conflict I would ask that you pull an item out of your claims in vote
For it's separately.
I think weíll leave a hand then go ahead
And all those details from these entire claim
Weíre going up
Make a motion when approved by clients with
With The exception Of Ironman Question
Is that a bill?
Bill Williams
Aye.
By, weíre going on the RLI surety bond with mayor
There was pulled out
Motion 2nd
Aye
Four minutes from June 5th
23 regar meeting in May 28th
223 special meetings
Second
Bill
Aye
Five, but I remember 23-25
Receiving an expending Joe Pollock Bill House insurance
Recovery funds
To reimburse their repair and maintenance account
That was used for the bill house repairs
This is very similar to what solid waste itís going
Going through doing except theyíre gonna take money within
In this same fund so in adjustment can move my back
This is where the sports took their budget
And they fixed that Joe Pollock field house
That had a plumbing issue
So now there re-insurance recovery funds are back
They need to buy things, and you know what?
They were budgeted by for them so weíre asking if it will be able
To spend this fifty five hours
Two two, three
Five
Six, and youíll fill lease agreement
To see if I have a multi-purpose sports complex
On the 808 in campus with MCFA
For fiscal year 23 24
So this is The eight annual bill
Agreement within CFA
It allows city to had same type of exacting number
And usage that other two partners at any oanim college
In line above what schools has
The only thing that has changed is the dates
And it expires June 30, 2020
Second
Aye
Seven
The clerk immediately emergency aligning for
Emergency purchase according to Section 2
There are three big processes
Emergency purchases at these solid waste transfer station
Much improved
Exit, aye
Aye
Aye, acceptance of power line in relocation
Five twenty-throde, utility easemits
From a kind rural water district
Riki and leases yates
James Franklin and Katherine Louise Williams
Herum & Sandra Jay Price
And Stephen Earl Halls
Most two approved, sorry
Estep
Eep
It's nine, a ward lease purchase agreement for
Q23-32
23 RAM
2500 crew cab truck
The first national bank
Give her related signing
And payment authority to city manager or his does need
Replacing an older model in the parks
On this track
Originally there were two orders
They've only been able
to get the financing
We sent out
Bit proposals
To seven banks
Security, US bank or best
Bank of Grand Lake, first national
And we had
The payments came in at eight
25% down
About 7.5x
But they ended up
Barely beating out
Bank of Grand Lake by thirty seven
$7.69
They've been a little on interest
but one didn't have a long fee charge
At first national kind through
So anyway, how is it?
Seven bitters we just need to pay for
To go ahead and get the start
One will attract me here
The truck, be yours
And I'm trying
to get the money
What do we replace in Brian?
It was just an old woman
We're adding two to play
In part of all our things
This is actually 21.22
But for 2 4 trucks
For a year and a day, it's $1
So there were some big traffic
Last couple years
I mean thank you very much
He said that
We have some new truck
So this is just something that you
Just trying to get a couple of years ago
And it's one able
To give more money
To the most of us
Hi
I'm Robert.
I've got three of them
This isn't your van
So what I've got for you this evening is
This isn't our network
Our employees have a plan
Is the payment cost bill and
The prime doctor's in job
And that it has been available
To continue to use the prime and hospital
For your all considering
That, i want
Tell me about an amazing job
Send event over to managing these health contracts
And managing our benefits and making sure that all of
Our city employees have a very rich benefit package
I think they've done an amazing job here at the City
Over to years, refining
Benefit packages
A lot is due
To Cindy in her efforts
Couldn't go without saying
Just curious why do we not use integrity?
Integrus has also part
We have another
PPO which is the community choice
And that's for our upcoming hospitals
Or if you wanted to go and tell us
or anywhere else in a state
You would use the preferred community choice
This was just for a job, basically
That makes sense
I make much more approval
Thank you
Hi
Discussion possible action
New airport
Cardinal
So many members of the council at a previous meeting
Where we had an discussion regarding the terminal
And therefore, in
The opportunity that it been laid out from there
One
Of one
That was a potential for revenue
Source or payback
The funds needed to accept the
Funds from their notice commission
We would have
To match a fund up front
From city
As we've discussed, what that looked like as you all know
Airport by itself
Doesn't stand low in general
A significant revenue source
Enough
Payback
The revenue that it generates
Generally goes back in the main
That's operations of your
In so,
So
And this building at city hall
Or basketball courts
Other facilities we have maintain
Maybe like a big pool
However
They airport itself
Does generate revenue
The community is a whole
It's utilized by our
Industry and Towns,
Significantly in other businesses
Sporting events
Things like that
This used for our tribes
Travel partners
Probably more than any
We see lot of Bill Coat
To access the utilize status
They find clients from all over
In the past few years
We have a lot of people
They are in broad and wide
But it's not an direct revenue
Generator, you know
As we said out
And talked about what would this look like
You had to start really
Realizing that
How will fund
A facility
If there was nothing
And most of that has been done
Over the years
Through either bonds or in last case
The significant renovations to this building
Was done in borrowing against
A rainy day found out a reserves
As we talked about the other day
In it was paid back
To
Emissue
Or
But one
I think that's a good idea
To make sure
That we talked about this correctly
So
We had to cover
They are not as commission
If Commissioner himself
Who was very clear
Our time is like
They would know our commitment
To the state
Regarding this project
And funding of that project
So they just have to know who else
If we needed a few more days
That would be fine
But
We also talked about what
This was looked like
As he explained it
He was going to be offering up a million dollar match
If the city could come off of
The first million
And anything over that
To make it
We can use our federal funds
But one
One important thing is this
Was not in project
Where by you were
Going
In next fiscal year
We were going to be doing it
In the first
Say
The next fiscal year
And we just took a budget war
He said they expenses are that
That is pretty minimal
Because you're being looking at design
But he says
It's gonna go on
You can see
The next you may be looking at
And the employment
They are built out and things like that
We also talked about
This is where a chief can get more specific
That council
Had agreed to
It was a significant renovation
To 5 year plans
A $5 million plan
90% of which
Was going
To 10% of that
They also said some
Those elements
Of the five year plan
Can actually be pushed out
Two years, six or seven
So those first two
There's a lot to put into that
We could take both funds and apply towards this project
And we had already committed about half a million
Next week
We commit it
Even that first million we thought
We'd have to do
And then the other half
The third leg of this whole presentation is
Currently,
Our paying ourselves back for
The renovation of the civic center
To about 370-1000 year
Which has been ongoing for several years
Next year's are final full payment
Then we have about a half payment
After that
Oh, I'm sorry
It was the other
So those two but it
But at 372
Was going to be paid up
We would take that same
We'd been budgeting today
And for previous fiscal years
To say the remaining balance of half a million
A couple years we'd be paying that off
So there are all things
There's our means in fact
We were talking about this and looking at it
Is how do you get to spend your money
And if I'm going back to the month
Then let me just spread out
From now on,
Our funds
It really becomes an decision of priority
And we want to jump now
To take the opportunity
It's a state funding match of a million dollars
If
We don't, then
Obviously that behind
Probably would be having this conversation
Few years from now
About how do you come up with it
To make our own
At some point
We've been spending 440,000
For airport for the next five years
And that's a city part of
Four and half million projects
Some were those
we push off
Then re-bample it
One was actually a term of renovations
Our due to schedule 200,004
That would be
Won't have access
Two hundred
Four is a project for one quality
And then some others would push off
So about half of it will be
Just washed with, over board of scuttle, spent their report
I appreciate the fact that we asked you guys
For a plan and came back
Very quickly so
Appreciate That
We said down in jails
To pull up this precious
Show us what has been borrowed against
Then they've been paid back
That's coming to an end
And that source
Essentially, it is kind of what we're saying
We just know will extend out a few more years
Can be able
You can literally take something
Something you could pay on for how many years
About ten or six
Since 2016
Maybe another couple year
Has there been
More mad again since
We've got our last meeting
I don't remember when we had our last meeting but
But i'm saying yes
Sorry about this
A lot in debt there, 100 times like that
And so other things
In the process of maybe redoing
We run your report
With us up here and do more
Leasing out operations
Generating more revenues
Through That
Means
But it does have some higher revenues
In the works
And that's just a matter of
I feel not pay work and then the girls had turns there
We do
An up here ready to start
To come in
Different operational ideas don't forward
So we see
Possibly for high revenues more
One more
Throw a question
No idea what i'm even talking about
When i asked this question
We talked about how the majority of our community
Doesn't use their reports and everything
What would it take to do an air show
Or can that be done?
It could me
There'd been a big undertaking
I think we would start with some fly ins
And thats just basically its put cards out there
Chilling piles, rubber flying
And advertising at low equipment
And then that's like air show
But a plane day
We're public invited to come out and look at just
G&A or craft
Build from there
Very doable they do them all over
Those are some of the things we've talked about
To bring in Air Show
It would be costly venture
That you could build up too
We'd love it
We'd like to get a month long flying poker run
We're people of the fly in your cursor car
Get all that signals, turn them into a
Basically it's poker on anyway
And I wrote for a month high hand wins
So we've discussed and planned some activities
For Airporters Generating Interest
People wouldn't go back out
I know the EAA, which is an aircraft association
They're local chapters do young e-health program
But they take kids for rides
And that had to quit at just some insurance requirements
Then we went a lot of fly with one adult and three kid in their airplane
That was observer
Some other planes couldn't take it
They would take one kid or made it almost impossible
To do that and allow their insurance as quit
I'd love to generate youth activity with the airport
Even if just a static display
And come out on C airplanes
Those are all of those we've talked about along
That idea
Be a dream, you'll need full flight air show
Just lots will spend some work
We have build up too
I think one of the things we probably didn't talk enough about
But they've talked a few years
Is that FBO?
That is what really, it's game changer for
The MyMoreeGenerable Airport
That FBO having someone like
Come in and take over
The management
Having investment at this terminal
Just fuel to your fire
Because now you know that city has made an investment
Now you've got your FBO that can come in and make other investments
Something ideal would be for maybe they didn't
They're looking at making an investment
In the OELO hangar out there
That's nothing I think we'd probably interested
If it wasnít a city business was made significant
Investment
But because
Their company is saying, i want to run a business
You give them any proof facility
To run that business out of
They're going to win more businesses
So now they are able
And leverage
More financially
To expand their business and even around the area like
The OELO hangar
It really has an opportunity
To be a force multiplier for
For this entire project
But FBO is big deal
I know David talked about it
Is there been any more discussion around sponsorships?
There have and that's something we're not done yet
We've continued to talk about the folks
We just talked a bit about what they are going
But thats everything you need
Because one of our opportunities
That is talking
If it were build in new terminal
It would be no internal
It would be a new terminal on site
And then re-innovating the old term
To use this as an educational facility
Which again, another force multiplier
What can we do with that?
We're going to start bringing in other aeronautics
Education and training
Open it nor wide open
That facilities really does lend itself
Very well
We have a lot of money and dollars
Five years
What is that money going to do?
I mean what would you plan on doing with the re-innovation
So my CFP projects, we had an apron rehab milled overlay
A planning designed for our taxiway
Crack sale
Remarking
Design
There's a line phase in the contracting phases
The runway is set on your magnetic heading right now
We are 35-1 7
Which I waited for the runway
And since that runway was put in
If we got a magnetic ship for a degree
So it's 38.16
We have north south runway
It would just, when an FAA set
At first time
The test on the slater
Was there no way to test them this later
Is it a very nice way
To redrapped those funds
Did they process?
Yes, that's exactly what aeronautics commission said
They would help us identify
Those projects were time-sensitive
That we're FAA requirements
It was still needed for time and fashion
As timely requirement
And we would push those to the end of a project
It'd be ideal if you got
Matching grant and federal government
Matched it for ya
That was one catch
We can't use Federal funds
For your match
But then, when are they over?
Over here is our amount
The two main mark
Our money in there
We can use a lot of funds
If it actually cost 2.2 million
We put up 1,000 and then we'd have to go
About 200 thousand
But what if you could do that with federal money?
Because the federal money
For half-may in there is getting over next five years
I don't know if its specifically
It would be traditional
So they get annual money as well
Okay, our answer
Is a five-million dollar grant
And we've paid the first half million
Then four and 1,5.2 million
We have a, it's 10% match
For those funds
We'll be having to match
But every year you get an amount from federal government
Yes
How much is that?
About 350
That's 300
But it gets every year that's not part of the grant
That could be used for
It would give me what
Use your foot towards to take 200
If its 2.2, you should just over time
We can get some things out
On a fly and we always do
Steaks by the mayor instead
I said no
Well i'll promote
Now
And on Facebook right now
Steads from Mayor Flyin
That would be Saturday, Mayor
And we'd like to
Make sure you don't want me to
I knew
So what's the exact action
We're possibly looking forward
The action i think we are looking for is that
If it was likely going
To give notice of your not exhibition
Citymime and a private program
You have so they'll add us
They project list
It gets submitted
We're still not 100% committed
I don't, i mean
Can you imagine that would be
Nobody's going to give your money
You are not gonna master spend right?
Just take back
What we will do is say
That being said
It did NOT ask if there was a
Closed by which
This is going to be a process
An extensive
We're simply saying that yes we are interested in
Yes, but you really get those funds
And I would like
To proceed with the next phase
So does The revitalization or building a new terminal
Give more revenue potential than say
Finishing our fence and closing it
We won't have one airplane ever
Say they could not stay
I guess i assumed it was a bigger deal
Just the 1 airplanes or whatever
And that's how you do
It does but this will be higher
Much higher, for turn on bus
The job and in house to help
That is what he said
But from my understanding
Correct me if i'm wrong
We are expecting a future grant to come along
That would help build the hangar that will be big enough
Yes, yes
Yeah
He just said it was
A few years, probably into this day
But If thats an outlier than its not really even
It's sort of huge concern
Obviously we definitely need to address it
What basically tells us is
If we take this next step
We start increasing our traffic
And then the FBO really takes off
Then there is opportunity to even grow that
And say further by utilizing those grant funds
To build out a hangar
That was an incredible program
You probably want it started looking at
Either of your fence or what's in front
That's a lot of work
I feel more comfortable about this
Knowing that it is not all one year
It was something changed for me
There really wasn't
But i'm looking at two cents
What we are paying in
Think you can use those same funds
To help buy the money
Something where to have them to build up
And then thats still looking
For outside sponsorships
So now make an ocean that were interested
I don't think he was clear of the privilege
That they wanted to do aeronautics
We need not here and so
So that's exactly it
i mean, imma have made a motion
But nobody is second
If we are not
Im gonna find me
And you got what?
To ask this
A million dollars
For their airport
You might be not being all this year
But you're asking for a million dollars
I can't get past what
Blast talking about
How many people use the airport
It's basically one percent
So i don t know
Like long term process of it
Im like to see new terminal there
Well, too
But i think there is many and million dollars to that
And I just check another box for our potential
For economic development
That's what we are thinking of
Well, the airport has been on a money either way
Either around home or with agreement
There
In their several things
We have had some
Those great examples
We have a lot of people coming to our airport
Now
13,000
People in this town are 100 or so come every day
For the two months that it's open
And we lose 116,7 thousand dollars per year
It is not generated enough revenue
To pay for itself
So you all fund
Yeah
Well
I think that's true
i
Think it is a community investment
And quality of life for many and for kids
As you don t see the correlation
The airport
It s not equality
That your betting on
You are betting in our house
Mine will grow
I think that it will get our stuff in the future
Could actually spark something
In a picture or we could hit up brick wall
Because you don t have
That's where
We challenge their port more defined ways to give public out there
Whether be fly ends
If flying and ride planes people are going
To come off of check themout
And if they can build anything
It is not bigger than the early event
Then at least go on people
They re able see it using
I also think that if we invest in the class of people
That are using facility
The one person will take a serious community
And maybe even more willing to talk
To their cohorts and there appears
My name is got
They re moving on, they have brand new facilities out
It s kind like
If any one has been proud
Of somebody who likes coming in
And escorting them around what we currently have
How would you?
We are going to remember two of our school systems
My not always started on the program there
I think my amnest talking
So at some point they re getting a partner with an airport
To do their tracks, if wanted that
The college was working
Yes, Dr. Stafford s huge part
You should have worked
I don t know if we could get a commitment from them
They would use us over anybody else at this point
But it will be nice to have
That s not the other way
Some commitments that were
We re getting in
The tribes or
To call out your email
You are going
To partner and listen
Do something like this
You know the short notice is
10 days left
Yeah, we have a same conversation
We got ten days
Not something that can get our entire
Fiscal Committee rally bond
That s an unfortunate
I wish you had more time
I think we should have a whole lot more people
So that s kind of wrong
Motion by Brian, then it will be the second
Don t call or any second
We re going on a quarter
You see what happens
He stepped
Williams
Thunder
K12
One new business committee which is the
Business and the post of this agenda
14 staff reports
14 mayor council community
Nalphus
So fiscal year
Through fiscal year
19 in 20
SELST action
From 5.30
Even through there
In the year 20.21
They jumped a 6 point two
On the $1 million jump
21 22
6,8 million
And then this year 2823
That we just finished up 7
So about 2 million
Jump and just raise your self-tax
Since the close of 1920
It was starting to climb and it
Was up 232,920
This year we closed that over a million
For the first time ever
And Racer sales tax would close
Over 7 million for
The first time ever
To 0.65 which is this street stadium
Had been pretty
Level between
1.1
So I want to congratulate this council
For your vision
And you're being open minded
To take chances and opportunities
That came from us
Thank for leading us with those decisions
Helping guys get there
But most of all
All wanted thank
You Guys
The department heads
To the work
And thank you
We appreciate your team
But we also appreciate our citizens
Because our citizens have stayed home with their
Dollars and they've spent money here
That was something that there's a big push
With to level local
Mandend her team help
Push through COVID
They kept doing it
Kowadower
The dollars still get in spin
And we appreciate our support
We appreciate that
Thank you all
Without You
We set up here and get these jobs
Then
You guys got there in pull it off
So Tyler & his crew is building
The infrastructure
Kevin, his crews doing the parks
Our parts are looking great
The infrastructure's working
We're going to be in the last couple of years
There's been a business you've
Been with permits and inspection
The stuff which is great
It was awesome that we were getting those things done
But it couldn't do without You Guys
So I appreciate each other one
One of your efforts
And its paying off for seeing
That more dollars are community keep spend here
More money than what we can sit
To get some work
Thanks
So next is the
Yeah
We have nothing to add
We'll head into
Executive session
Thank you
Good bye